Finding Aid for Friends of the Jordan River Watershed records
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Friends of the Jordan River Watershed records 1967-2012, 1990-2008
Friends of the Jordan River Watershed.
7 linear feet
2013052 Aa 2
The Friends of the Jordan River Watershed. Records contains the organizational and non-organizational records of conservation activities pertaining to the Jordan River and other fresh water bodies in the northwest corner of Michigan's Lower Peninsula.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was received from the Friends of the Jordan River Watershed, Inc. (Donor no. 10846 ) in November 2012.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
In December of 1990, thirty-three citizens in Michigan incorporated the Friends of the Jordan River Watershed (FOJ) as a non-profit organization with the stated mission to conserve the natural resources and protect the environmental quality of the Jordan River and its watershed, a land area covering roughly 125 square miles in Antrim, Charlevoix, and Otsego counties. FOJ has its beginnings in "Save the Jordan" steering committee established in 1957 to organize study of the Jordan River, its tributaries and the watershed. Organized efforts to maintain the natural resources of the Jordan River began as early as 1968 with a public campaign in Charlevoix County to "Save the Jordan." An early success of the campaign was the State of Michigan's designation of the Jordan River as "wild and scenic" under the state's Natural Rivers Act of 1970, the state's first river to achieve such a designation.
Because of the concern about development and energy extraction, researchers undertook measures to survey the watershed and its encompassing wildlife. These efforts led to several key reports and studies that guided the FOJ in its beginning stages of organization and incorporation. Over its two decades of existence, the organization has partnered with many local municipalities in the northwest corner of the Lower Peninsula of Michigan on projects or initiatives affecting water quality and the ecosystem.
In recent years, FOJ has focused its attention on a number of different issues, including legislative and executive efforts to combat the effects of hydraulic fracturing ("fracking") in the watershed area and educational outreach to K-12 schoolchildren in East Jordan. Responding to a lawsuit filed by two local municipalities (Antrim County and Star Township) and FOJ, in August of 2009 a judge in Michigan's 13th Circuit Court (Antrim County) issued an indefinite block against an energy company that sought to drill a deep-injection disposal well near the community of Alba, Michigan. The Alba well victory aligns with many of the other advocacy initiatives FOJ has pursued in its nearly twenty-five year history.
The Friends of the Jordan River Watershed. Records makes a significant contribution to understanding late twentieth and early twenty-first century environmental advocacy within the state of Michigan, especially in the Lower Peninsula's northwest corner as it relates to conservation of freshwater systems. Further, FOJ's engagement with state and local government agencies illuminates the ways in which it has been able to increase the political and regulatory salience of environmental protection, despite and amidst the simultaneous rising influence of energy companies. The records will be useful for any researcher seeking to explore these dynamics and many others related to environmental justice.
The Friends of the Jordan River Watershed. Records provides evidence of the organization's efforts to maintain the environmental and water quality of the Jordan River and its supporting water system. The collection is arranged into two series: Internal Business and External Business.
Subjects:
Friends of the Jordan River Watershed.; Jordan River Watershed (Antrim County and Charlevoix County, Mich.)--Environmental conditions.; Conservation of natural resources--Michigan.; Environmental monitoring--Michigan--Jordan River (Antrim County and Charlevoix County); Watersheds--Michigan.
Genre/Form:
CD-ROMs.; Photographs.
- Internal Business
  The Internal Business series is divided into four subseries: Administration, Initiatives, Surveys and Studies, and Publications. Each of the subseries follows an alphabetical arrangement. The Administration subseries documents mainly the operations of the FOJ Board of Directors and Executive Officers and covers the years 1968 to 2006, including board meeting minutes, agendas, and annual meeting minutes. The Initiatives subseries contains the bulk of the collection that reflect the activities of the organization, including its participation in the Alba Well injection case, application for state land reserve status, and involvement in mineral exchange propositions. Scientific investigations pertaining to the Jordan River, its watershed, and nearby waterways can be found in the Surveys and Studies subseries, spanning the years 1968 to 2008. Lastly, early organizational newsletters, educational brochures, and an assortment of clippings are located in the Publications subseries.
  - Administration
    - Administrative and financial files 1995-2006 (scattered) (Box 1)
    - Annual events, agendas and minutes 1990-1997 (scattered) (Box 1)
    - Annual meeting handouts and extra handout materials 1990-1994 (Box 1)
    - Annual meeting minutes and reports 1991-2000, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Attorneys fees and settlements 1997-1998 (Box 1)
    - Awards 1997-1999 (Box 1)
    - Banquet planning documents 1994, 1995 (Box 1)
    - "Beaver Management," 1998 (Box 1)
    - Benefit concert 1995, 1997 (Box 1)
    - Billboard purchase 2008 (Box 1)
    - Birch Bank Canoe acquisition 2002 (Box 1)
    - Board minutes and agendas 1995-2003, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Bulk mail forms 1996 (Box 1)
    - Communication 2003 (Box 1)
    - Contact information for Michigan environmental organizations undated (Box 1)
    - Founding documents 1989-1994 (Box 1)
    - Greeting cards undated (Box 1)
    - Insurance policies and accounts 2000-2003 (Box 1)
    - Jordan River Watershed Center building photographs 2001 (Box 1)
    - Jordan River Watershed Center early concepts and historical photos undated (Box 1)
    - Mailing and membership list 1990-1994 (scattered) (Box 1)
    - Master membership list undated (Box 1)
    - Michigan State Legislature contact list 1999 (Box 1)
    - Press and media contact lists undated (Box 1)
    - "Save the Jordan" first annual report and clippings 1968, 1971 (Box 1)
    - Save the Jordan River steering committee minutes, maps, zoning permits 1967-1993 (scattered) (Box 1)
    - Strategic planning reports 1996-2000, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Travel and expense vouchers 1994-2000 (Box 2)
    - Treasurer's reports 2001-2005 (Box 2)
  - Initiatives
    - Adopt-A-Highway application 2001 (Box 2)
    - Alba Well injection court case 2008-2009 (Box 2)
    - Civil Environmental discourse project 2002 (Box 2)
    - Cosner Preserve grant from the Rotary Charities of Traverse City 1996-1999 (Box 2)
    - Clean Michigan initiative 1998 (Box 2)
    - Defend the Jordan campaign 1996, 1998 (Box 2)
    - Direct Impact on Rivers and Trails (D.I.R.T.) grant 1999 (Box 2)
    - EPA Grant, Alba Schools Partners for Environmentally Educated Communities (PEEC) Headwaters initiative 1996-1998, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Fisheries committee agendas, plans, and questionnaires 1983-1994 (scattered) (Box 2)
    - Grant application for the Michigan Coastal Management Program 1996 (Box 2)
    - Hydrocarbon development planning proposal 1997-1998 (Box 2)
    - Jordan River Run/Walk logistics documents 1996-2000, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Jordan Valley Management Area state land reserve application materials 1999-2000, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Jordan Valley Management plan 1974, 1975 (Box 2)
    - K & K Construction, Inc. v. Department of Natural Resources contributions, 1997, 1998 (Box 2)
    - Lower Jordan River "wild and scenic" designation 1995-1996 (Box 2)
    - Ludington State Park state land reserve petition undated (Box 2)
    - Michigan Department of Environmental Quality Surface Water Quality Division volunteer monitoring program 1997 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Groundwater/Freshwater Protection Act 247 1994 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Groundwater Stewardship Program 1999 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Natural Resources and Environmental Protection Act of 1994, 1995 (Box 2)
    - Michigan State University Extension (MSUE) Master Gardener volunteer applications 1997-1999 (Box 2)
    - Mineral exchange background information 1971-1997 (scattered) (Box 3)
    - Mineral exchange oil and gas well photos 2004-2006, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Mineral exchange proposition between Jordan Valley Management Area and Lee's Petroleum, LLC 1997 (Box 3)
    - Natural Rivers Zoning testimony 1974 (Box 3)
    - Petition final draft for state land reserve designation and testimony 2000 (Box 3)
    - Pinney and Timber Bridge construction proposals 1996-2000 (Box 3)
    - Post-production costs testimony and publications 1994-1996 (Box 3)
    - Project F.I.S.H. 2000 (Box 3)
    - Riparian residents files-- Lower Jordan / Deer Creek / Warner Creek 1994-1995 (Box 3)
    - Riverlife grant materials 1995-1996 (Box 3)
    - Riverlife meeting agendas, minutes, and correspondence 1995-1998 (Box 3)
    - Riverlife -- Michigan Environmental Council grant 1996 (Box 3)
    - Riverlife -- partnership agreement 1997 (Box 3)
    - Scenic beauty proposal to the State of Michigan 1996 (Box 3)
    - Sportsman's Park project 1998 (Box 3)
    - State Land Reserve Act overview and legislation 1998 (Box 3)
    - Watershed initiative 1992-1997 (scattered) (Box 3)
  - Surveys and Studies
    - Bay Harbor CERCLA Site review undated (Box 3)
    - Boyne River Subwatershed road-stream crossing inventories undated (Box 3)
    - East Jordan High School microbial source tracking (MST) student water quality reports 1998, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Feasibility study for Tourist Park, Murphy Park and Sportsman's Park in East Jordan 1998 (Box 3)
    - Fox River natural river plan 1995 (Box 3)
    - Gaylord Forest Management Unit compartment review presentation 2008 (Box 3)
    - Jordan River assessment and management options 1997-2000 (Box 3)
    - Jordan River conservation project description undated (Box 3)
    - Jordan River fishery data and reports 1977-1995 (scattered and undated) (Box 3)
    - Jordan River Fishing and Canoeing Recreational Access Site Survey 2000 (Box 3)
    - Jordan River property owners list 1998 (Box 3)
    - Jordan River trout surveys 1987, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Jordan River Valley maps undated (Box 3)
    - Jordan River Watershed Center drafts undated (Box 3)
    - Jordan River Watershed Center master plan study 1999-2000 (Box 3)
    - Jordan River Watershed Center sketches and plans 1998-1999 (Box 3)
    - Jordan River Watershed erosion and sedimentation control proposal 1995-1997 (Box 3)
    - Jordan River Watershed management plan 1972-1997 (scattered and undated) (Box 3)
    - Jordan River zoning maps undated (Box 4)
    - Lake Charlevoix Shoreline / Smaller Tributaries road-stream crossing inventories undated (Box 4)
    - Lake Charlevoix tributary survey 1989 (Box 4)
    - Lake Charlevoix Watershed project road-stream crossing inventories 2001 (Box 4)
    - Lake Charlevoix water quality report 1996 (Box 4)
    - Maps and plans related to Jordan River erosion sites 1990-1996 (Box 4)
    - Maps of Lower Jordan River / Deer Creek property owners 1995 (Box 4)
    - Michigan Department of Environmental Quality staff report on total maximum daily loads (TMDL's) 1998 (Box 4)
    - Michigan Sea Grant College Program annual reports 2004, 2005 (Box 4)
    - Natural River Plans of the Pine and Upper Manistee Rivers 2002-2003 (Box 4)
    - Phase II final report: assessing changes in private property values along designated natural rivers in Michigan 1998 (Box 4)
    - Preliminary survey of the Jordan River Watershed 1968 (Box 4)
    - Proposed solutions to sea lamprey 1968-1992 (Box 4)
    - Sample survey 1989-1992 (Box 4)
    - Sportsman's Park MST Data 1998, 2004 (Box 4)
    - U.S. 131 Corridor Study 1997 (Box 4)
    - Water quality monitoring equipment list, inventory, and data 1993-2000 (scattered and undated) (Box 4)
  - Publications
    - Brochures undated (Box 4)
    - Calendars 2007-2012 (Box 4)
    - Clippings 1977-2007 (scattered) (Box 4)
    - Frey Foundation grant announcement 1994, 1996 (Box 4)
    - Jordan Valley Voices newsletters, 1995-2014, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Jordan Valley Voices: Resource Book, 2002 (Box 4)
    - Press releases 2001, undated (Box 4)
- External Business
  The External Business series is divided into four subseries: Allied Organizations, Municipalities, Subject Files, and Publications. Each of the subseries follows an alphabetical arrangement. FOJ remains informed on the activities of similar environmental organizations throughout the state, region, and country. These activities are well documented in the Allied Organizations subseries. Represented are newsletters, bulletins, and annual reports of groups located primarily in northern Michigan, but also materials from other parts of the state. The Municipalities subseries is a selection of local statutes, ordinances, and plans impacting the work of FOJ in the area. The municipalities most represented are Antrim County and the City of East Jordan. The Subject Files range from 1996 to 2012 and address one of the most pressing concerns of FOJ, hydraulic fracturing ("fracking"). The Publications subseries is comprised of newspaper articles, maps, and other published materials relating to issues of interest to FOJ or other environmental organizations.
  - Allied Organizations
    - American Rivers reports, publications, and strategic plan 1996-1997 (Box 4)
    - Anglers of the Au Sable newsletters 2005 (Box 4)
    - Antrim Conservation District grant application and annual report 1997 (Box 4)
    - Au Sable Institute of Environmental Studies publications and newsletters 2000-2003 (Box 4)
    - Boardman River Group newsletters 1999, 2000 (Box 4)
    - Charlevoix Conservation District newsletter 2001 (Box 4)
    - Charlevoix County Land Conservancy newsletters and publications 1998-1999 (Box 4)
    - Citizens for Alternatives to Chemical Contamination newsletters 1999-2000 (Box 4)
    - Conservation News Service summit agendas 2001-2003 (Box 4)
    - Conservation Resource Alliance clippings, programs, proposals and newsletters 1996-2005 (scattered) (Box 4)
    - Educational pamphlets and brochures of other environmental groups undated (Box 4)
    - Elk River-Chain of Lakes conservation plans 1994-2000 (Box 4)
    - Elk River-Chain of Lakes Watershed Project Summary undated (Box 4)
    - Enviro-Mich email list 1999 (Box 4)
    - Environmental Education Consortium 1998 (Box 4)
    - Flint River Watershed Coalition newsletter 2006 (Box 5)
    - Forest Recreation Advisory Committee meeting agendas and minutes 1995 (Box 5)
    - Friends of the Boyne River, Inc. and Boyne City Wastewater settlement agreement 2004-2005, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Friends of the Boyne River, Inc. bulletins and clippings 1998-1999 (Box 5)
    - Friends of the Cedar River Watershed, Inc. grant application 1999 (Box 5)
    - Friends of the Cedar River Watershed, Inc. settlement agreement 1997-2000 (Box 5)
    - Friends of the Detroit River membership form and newsletter 1998-2000 (Box 5)
    - Friends of St. Clair Lake-Six Mile Lake Natural Area maps and newsletter 1995, undated (Box 5)
    - Grand Traverse Regional Land Conservancy educational pamphlets, clippings, and annual reports 1997-2003 (scattered) (Box 5)
    - Grass River Natural Area newsletters, guides, and annual reports 1997-2003 (scattered and undated) (Box 5)
    - Great Lakes Aquatic Habitat newsletter 2003 (Box 5)
    - Great Lakes Commission annual reports and newsletters 1997-1999 (Box 5)
    - Great Lakes Fisheries Trust annual report and proposal 1998-2000 (Box 5)
    - Institute of Water Research (Michigan State University) newsletters 1995-1996 (Box 5)
    - Jordan River Conservation tour plans and routes 1990, 1992 (Box 5)
    - Jordan River Water Commission reports and meeting minutes 1968-1971, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Kitchen Farms trial judgment and news coverage 1999, 2000 (Box 5)
    - Lake Charlevoix Association annual meeting proceedings, correspondence, and publications 1995-1996 (Box 5)
    - Lake Michigan Federation publications and pamphlets 1997-1999 (Box 5)
    - Land Information Access Association proposals 2000-2002 (Box 5)
    - Little Traverse Conservancy annual reports, newsletters, and publications 1992-2002 (scattered and undated) (Box 5)
    - Little Traverse Conservancy newsletters 2000-2002 (Box 5)
    - Lower Jordan Conservation and Recreation Committee meeting agendas 1995-1997 (Box 5)
    - Lower Jordan Conservation and Recreation Committee stakeholder participation form undated (Box 5)
    - Lower Jordan Conservation and Recreation Committee strategic plan 1997 (Box 5)
    - Michigan Communities Land Use Coalition newsletters 1994-1996 (Box 5)
    - Michigan Environmental Council newsletters and publications 1995-2003 (scattered in 3 folders) (Box 5)
    - Michigan Lake and Stream Associations annual conference announcement 2003 (Box 5)
    - Michigan Land Resource Project summary 2001 (Box 5)
    - Michigan Land Use Institute memos, publications, and meeting agendas 1995-1999 (scattered in 2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Michigan River Network contact and participant lists 1999-2000 (Box 5)
    - Michigan United Conservation Clubs publications 1999 (Box 5)
    - Natural Resources Commission meeting minutes 2000 (Box 5)
    - Natural Waters Committee mission statement undated (Box 5)
    - O.I.L. Energy Corp. petition for compulsory pooling 1996 (Box 5)
    - Pere Marquette Watershed Council Inc. minutes, directories, and newsletters 1995-2002 (Box 5)
    - Pine River Watershed Restoration Project partnership agreement undated (Box 5)
    - Power Coalition meeting minutes and announcements 2009 (Box 5)
    - The Orion Society magazine 2003 (Box 5)
    - Three Lakes Association newsletters, reports, and statements 1995-2000 (Box 6)
    - Tip of the Mitt Watershed Council annual reports, newsletters, and correspondence 1988-2002 (scattered in 2 folders) (Box 6)
    - United States Forest Service Flowing Waters newsletter 1993 (Box 6)
    - Wagbo Peace Center pamphlets and newsletters 1996-1999 (scattered and undated) (Box 6)
    - Watershed council organizational bylaws, newsletters, and articles of incorporation 1991-2002 (scattered and undated) (Box 6)
  - Municipalities
    - Alcona County v. Wolverine Environmental Production, Inc. appeal, 1998 (Box 6)
    - Antrim County, Area Attractions: Trails, Campgrounds, Restaurants, etc. undated (Box 6)
    - Antrim County Board of Commissioners resolution to ban oil drilling in the Jordan Valley Management Area 1996-1997 (Box 6)
    - Antrim County General and Survey Gazette Art, 1991, 1999 (Box 6)
    - Antrim County GIS implementation meeting 1998, 1999 (Box 6)
    - Antrim County manufacturers, base industries, and list of all other Antrim County businesses 1998 (Box 6)
    - Antrim County mineral and gas well ownership, location, and maps 1999-2000 (Box 6)
    - Antrim County Soil Erosion and Stormwater Runoff Control Ordinance 1993-1996 (Box 6)
    - (Antrim County) U.S. Environmental Protection Agency draft permit for Schroeder Well 2002 (Box 6)
    - Antrim County Watershed Festival reports 1998 (Box 6)
    - Antrim County Wetlands permit application 1998 (Box 6)
    - Antrim County Wetlands background information circa 1990s (Box 6)
    - Antrim County Wetlands clippings 2002 (Box 6)
    - Antrim County Wetlands court case 1997-1999 (Box 6)
    - Antrim County Ordinance for the Protection and Regulation of Wetland Areas in Antrim County, Mich. 2000 (Box 6)
    - Boyne City wastewater disposal plan 2004 (Box 6)
    - Charlevoix County 2022 draft vision statement, 2003 (Box 6)
    - Crawford County proposed zoning ordinance undated (Box 6)
    - East Jordan history 1995 (Box 6)
    - East Jordan Hotel project status report undated (Box 6)
    - East Jordan maps and City Board & Commissions lists 1996 (Box 6)
    - East Jordan permit application to the Michigan Department of Environmental Quality 2003 (Box 6)
    - East Jordan proposed lease agreement with Friends of the Jordan 1999 (Box 6)
    - East Jordan storm drain maps 2000, 2005 (Box 6)
    - East Jordan zoning code undated (Box 6)
    - Grand Traverse band request for library and archive 2005 (Box 6)
    - Michigan Department of Natural Resources and Environment compartment reviews in Antrim, Charlevoix, and Otsego Counties 2000-2004 (Box 6)
    - Otsego County planning and zoning code 1997 (Box 6)
    - South Arm Township zoning ordinance 1981 (Box 6)
  - Subject Files
    - Environmental education materials undated (Box 6)
    - Environmental resources bibliography 1994 (Box 6)
    - Forestry 1993-1996 (Box 6)
    - Fracking 2008-2012 (Box 6)
    - Greenbelts and greenways 1997-1998 (Box 6)
    - Oil and gas leasing educational publications 1999, 2002 (Box 6)
    - Land use 2000 (Box 6)
    - Property rights 1990-1996 (scattered and undated) (Box 6)
    - Tourism 1997, 1998 (Box 6)
    - Trust fund 1999 (Box 6)
    - Vance building history and Vance family history undated (Box 6)
    - Watersheds undated (Box 6)
    - Zoning 1996 (Box 6)
  - Publications
    - Building a Sense of Place: A Cooperative Approach to Discovering and Preserving Community Character (CD-ROM included), 1999 (Box 6)
    - Clippings on exotic species undated (Box 6)
    - Environmental Education Consortium state science standards 1999-2000 (Box 6)
    - Lists of Michigan legislators 1999-2000 (Box 6)
    - Michigan Public Service Commission statute and administrative code undated (Box 6)
    - Michigan snowmobile trail maps undated (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous clippings 1967-2012, 11 folders (Box 7)
    - North Country Trail maps and pamphlets 2006, undated (Box 7)
    - Planning & Zoning News magazine, 1999, 2000, 3 issues (Box 7)
    - State of Michigan oil and gas lease auction catalog 2002 (Box 7)
    - Stewardship Quarterly (Journal of Natural Resources Conservation for Northern Michigan), 1994, 1995 (Box 7)
    - Sustainable Development Self-Assessment Guide 1997 (Box 7)
    - Wade-Trim publications 2000 (Box 7)